<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Getting Started</title>
        <author email="dennis.reedy@gmail.com">Dennis Reedy</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Where to Start?">
            <div class="section"><h3>Release Information</h3></div>
            <p>
                Rio is distributed under the <a href="license.html">Apache License, version 2.0</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Rio requires JDK 1.6.x or greater.
            </p>

            <div id="tipbox">
                <img src="images/check.gif"/>
                Although not required, setting the JAVA_HOME environment
                variable to point to the home of a Java 6 (or later) installation
                is always a good idea.
            </div>
            <p>
                Rio is distributed with dependencies. Dependencies are additional
                software required for running Rio. Note that each of these libraries
                is subject to the respective license; check the respective project
                distribution/website before using any of them in your own environment.
            </p>
            <p>
                The distribution includes the following third party technology: Apache River 2.2.1 (Jini),
                Hyperic SIGAR, Commons Compress 1.0, Groovy, SLF4J, Logback and the
                Prefuse Visualization Toolkit.
            </p>


            <div class="section"><h3>Installing</h3></div>
            <p>
                To install Rio on Linux or OS/X, unzip the distribution package
                to the desired installation directory. For example, to install into <tt>/opt</tt>:
            </p>
            <p>
                <tt>unzip rio-5.0-M3.zip -d /opt</tt>
            </p>
            <p>This creates a directory called <tt>rio-5.0-M3</tt> under <tt>/opt</tt></p>

            <p>
                To install Rio on Windows, unzip the distribution package to the
                desired installation directory. You should use a zip application such
                as 7zip, not the built-in folder decompression. Note that both Windows
                and Java 5 have some issues with long file names and file paths, as
                well as with spaces in directory names. We recommend installing into a
                directory of your chosen drive, and ensuring that directory names do not
                have spaces (like C:\Program Files).
            </p>
            <div class="section"><h3>Examining the distribution</h3></div>

            <p>
                Once you have unzipped the distribution, you will have a
                rio-5.0-M3 directory containing the following items:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li><b>bin</b> - The directory that contains command to start Rio services</li>
                <li><b>config</b> - Directory that contains configuration for Rio services and platform</li>
                <li><b>deploy</b> - The default deploy directory used to serve deployed application resources.</li>
                <li><b>docs</b> - The directory that contains API documentation, and other documentation</li>
                <li><b>examples</b> - Contains examples of how to develop and deploy applications using Rio</li>
                <li><b>lib</b> - The directory where the JAR files are located.</li>
                <li><b>lib/hyperic</b> - The directory where Hyperic SIGAR JAR files are located.</li>
                <li><b>lib/logging</b> - The directory where logging JAR files are located.</li>
                <li><b>lib/resolver</b> - The directory where Rio and Aether resolver JAR files are located.</li>
                <li><b>lib-dl</b> - The directory where the client (download) JAR files are located.</li>
                <li><b>logs</b> - This directory contains log files for Rio</li>
                <li><b>policy</b> - The directory that contains a policy file</li>
                <li><b>src</b> - Source code for Rio</li>
            </ul>

            <div class="section"><h3>Developing Services</h3></div>

            <p>
                You can look at the examples provided, as well as checking put the following tutorials:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="tutorial/service/service-intro.html">Service tutorial</a></li>
                <li><a href="tutorial/service-exec/service-exec-intro.html">Service exec tutorial</a></li>
            </ul>

            <div class="section"><h3>Examples</h3>
                <p>
                    Please make sure to examine the examples provided. An overview of all the examples
                    can be found <a href="examples/index.html">here</a>.</p>
            </div>

            <div class="section"><h3>Project Creation</h3>
                <p>You can create a Rio project in seconds using the
                <a href="rio-archetype.html">Rio Archetype</a>. Simply run:
                </p>
                <div class="source">
                    <pre>RIO_HOME/bin/rio create-project</pre>
                </div>
                <p>
                    You will be prompted to enter the artifactId, service to
                    create (this will be the classname of the service interface),
                    the groupId, version and package name.
                </p>
            </div>

            <div class="section"><h3>Starting Rio</h3>
                <p>
                    The <tt>RIO_HOME/bin</tt> directory contains starter script
                    (and .cmd) files to start Services and Utilities provided by Rio.
                </p>

                <div id="infobox">
                    <img src="images/information.gif"/>
                    Note, you should make sure that you set the <tt>RIO_HOME</tt>
                    environment variable to point to the directory that you have
                    installed the Rio distribution.
                </div>

                <p>
                    The <tt>rio</tt> script is the the command and control utility
                    for starting Rio services and the Rio command line interface.
                    All of the other scripts are wrappers around the <tt>rio</tt>
                    script. The convention for starting services using the <tt>rio</tt>
                    scripts is as follows:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><tt>rio start</tt> <i>service-starter</i></li>
                </ul>

                <p>
                    For example:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><tt>rio start cybernode</tt><br/>
                        <p>Will use the <tt>config/start-cybernode.groovy</tt> file</p>
                    </li>
                    <li><tt> rio start all</tt><br/>
                        <p>Will use the <tt>config/start-all.groovy</tt> file</p>
                    </li>
                </ul>

                <p>The following scripts are shortcuts for starting the basic services in Rio:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li><b>cybernode</b> - Starts a Cybernode and a Webster on an anonymous port</li>
                    <li><b>monitor</b> - Starts a Provision Monitor, a transient Jini Lookup service
                        and a Webster on port 9010</li>
                    <li><b>webster</b> - Starts a Webster on port 9010</li>
                    <li><b>startall</b> - Starts a Webster on port 9010, a Cybernode,
                        Provision Monitor and a transient Jini Lookup Service</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    By just running <tt>rio</tt>, you will be put into the interactive command line shell:
                </p>
                <div class="source">
<pre>Welcome to the Rio Interactive Shell Program. You can interact
with the Rio using the following commands :

list     http     deploy   destroy  dir
help     pwd      jconsole redeploy set
undeploy cd       ls       stats

For help on any of these commands type help [command].
To leave this program type quit

rio&gt; _</pre>
                </div>
            </div>        
        </section>
    </body>
</document>