<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Welcome to the Rio Project</title>
        <author email="dennis.reedy@gmail.com">Dennis Reedy</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Tomcat Example">
            <p>
               The Tomcat example demonstrates how to activate and manage an existing (external)
                technology using the Rio exec framework. In this example, Tomcat is installed,
                deployed and started. The environment is set allowing Tomcat to be managed by JMX.
            </p>

            <p>
                The example also shows how a declarative watch can be used to monitor JMX managed
                attributes, and set thresholds for manage-able Tomcat attributes.
                Our example shows how the MBean for the thread pool that handles
                incoming Web requests can be observed.
            </p>


            <div id="infobox">
                <img src="../../images/information.gif"/>
                The Rio Service Exec framework is currently available for POSIX based systems only
            </div>
            <p>
                Our example will create a Service Control Adapter (SCA) to activate
                and monitor a Tomcat instance. The example requires no coding, just
                configuration of the OperationalString.
            </p>


            <div class="section"><h3>Building the example</h3>
                The Tomcat example is built as a Maven project, and uses the
                Maven Rio Plugin to produce a single artifact; the Operational String Archive (OAR).
            <p>
                Running <tt>mvn install</tt> will result in the execution of an
                integration test that uses the Rio test infrastructure, where
                Tomcat will be provisioned, extracted and started.
            </p>
            </div>
            <div class="section"><h3>Running the example</h3>
                Look <a href="running.html">here</a> for information on running the example
            </div>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>